<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Essays of love and marriage being letters written by two gentlemen, one dissuading from love, the other an answer thereunto : with some characters and other passages of wit.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H64A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11545</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11824483</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11824483</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49622</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45495)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49622)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 32:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Essays of love and marriage being letters written by two gentlemen, one dissuading from love, the other an answer thereunto : with some characters and other passages of wit.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 103 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Love.</term>
               <term>Marriage.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49622:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49622:1"/>
            <p>ESSAYS OF LOVE AND MARRIAGE: Being LETTERS written by two Gentlemen; One diſſuading from LOVE, the other an Anſwer thereunto. With ſome CHARACTERS and other Paſſages of Wit.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Si quando gravabere curis,</l>
               <l>Haec lege, pro moeſtae medicamine mentis habete.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Brome</hi> at the Gun in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="owners_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:49622:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>horse and griffin flanking Egerton coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <p>SIC DONEC</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Right Hon.<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> Scroop Eger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Earl of Bridgwater V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſcount Brackley Baron of Elſmere 1703</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="bookseller_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49622:2"/>
            <head>THE Book-ſeller to the Reader.</head>
            <p>'<seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Is Expectation that makes the beſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and therefore I queſtion not what acceptance this Second Edition of the <hi>Eſſays of Love and Marriage</hi> may find. I was very ſeaſonably preſented with a ſhort Diſcourſe, conteining what is remarkable in the late Piece called, <hi>Reflections on Marriage,</hi> before the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this to the Preſs. Which being ſuitable as well in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject as in its Bulk to the former Eſſays, I have linked them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:49622:3"/>It matters not whether I praiſe it with a commendatory Frontiſpiece. Good Wine wants no Buſh. But not being in this an indifferent Judge, I might not in my Attempt be much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded.
<q>
                  <hi>Laudat venales qui vult extru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere merces.</hi>
               </q> However, I hope the ſame Fate will not attend this as does the Subject now adays to remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courted, but to find Acceptance with all, which will anſwer my Deſign to pleaſe you, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit my ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>Hen. Brome.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49622:3"/>
               <head>To his Honoured Friend, being in Love.</head>
               <head>I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>True Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BUt that I know <hi>hereſie</hi> is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhionable, and <hi>madneſs</hi> the time-Livery, thou wouldſt force me to no little wonder, which way poſſible thou ſhouldſt ſtumble into <hi>Love,</hi> be ſick and ſottiſh in <hi>Love,</hi> loſt as well to <hi>reaſon</hi> as good <hi>company,</hi> lock d up from all the world but thy own thoughts, and only converſant with thy ſelf; yet formerly pleaſant and affable, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deſired of Society, and one that I know has lived no <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choret</hi> upon Earth, nor yet haſt had
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49622:4"/>thine eyes tied up to any one face, but haſt both view'd and diſcourſt with variety of <hi>Beauties;</hi> nay, I dare ſay, not guilty of the Ignorance of more: yet that after ſo many <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidotes,</hi> thou ſhouldſt be ſo far fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from thy primitive goodneſs, as to loſe thy ſelf in <hi>dotage,</hi> and that dotage on one <hi>creature,</hi> and that creature a <hi>woman,</hi> and call it <hi>Love</hi> too, really next to a miracle, is my only Admiration. Prethee do not miſcall thy diſeaſe, and be ſick of <hi>luſt,</hi> and complain of Love: I can never believe that that noble Paſſion can be the ruine of its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; neither will I ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage it, as to make a <hi>woman</hi> its object. If there be Love, 'tis to <hi>Heaven,</hi> Virtue, thy Country, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Kinred, Friends, or what is of worth: but to the Female Sex, and in thy ſenſe where Senſuality
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49622:4"/>cannot but have an intereſt, though licenc'd by an Ordinance, 'tis only Love ſcandal'd, it being (to the pity of the poor Paſſion I ſpeak it) but concupiſcence handſomly bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht, or a carnal appetite ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly intitled. And therefore could I never win my judgment to affirm, that the moſt eager of ſinners were in love with ſin, but only tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſeduced to a vicious doting; they did rather erroneouſly affect, than truly love. But let me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into thy Paſſion: what, is it from the paint of Nature, thoſe beautiful flowers of red and white? Methinks thou ſhouldſt as well be enamour'd with thy Miſtris' Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture as her Body; for even that too is not excuſable from Art, and may be the worſt drawn. <hi>Frank,</hi> he that marries for a face, marries for a year; 'tis not a Summer ſince
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49622:5"/>thy deſires wrought as ſtrongly upon Miſtris <hi>M.R.</hi> as now on this, and may be on as good a cauſe; yet how ſoon did a little diſeaſe wither both her Beauty and thy Love? and I hope thou haſt not indented either with Sickneſs or Time for this. Canſt thou be ſo prodigal of thy Affection as to waſte it on ſuch incertainties? bind up thy ſelf to love for an Age, when the cauſe of that love may periſh in a Moneth? But I tell thee, <hi>Frank,</hi> beauty is a Chimera, and has no being in nature: Every man makes his own Miſtris, and juſt ſo much luſtre do's he find in her, as firſt his fanſie gives her. For I dare challenge thee to ſhew me but one Face in the whole world, that all opinions will give in for beautiful; ſo that Lovers, as thou call'ſt them, are but in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49622:5"/>number of Pagans, they but wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that Idol which themſelves have made. May be thou wilt tell me of manners, carriage and virtue, I am very glad to hear of it; but let not thy Paſſion hang in thy eyes when thou lookeſt on them; for many of them, their Geſtures are but School-poſtures, and ſeem ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like a Motion than a Carriage. Conſider that in the preſence of their Servants they are on the Stage, and 'tis rather Action than Behaviour: it may be wert thou a peeper on them in thier with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing rooms, thou wouldſt as much wiſh thine eyes cloſed then, as now open. For their virtues, as I will not diſallow the judgment of that Reverend Doctor, That 'tis poſſible to find ſome virtue in ſome women: ſo I cannot believe there is ſuch a grand ſtock of it in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49622:6"/>any of them, as to command any man out of his ſenſes for the love of it; but I ſuppoſe, as we more wonder to find a Diamond on the ſhore than on the rock: ſo but a ſpark of virtue in a woman gets greater reverence than a bodied luſtre in the nobler Sex; for 'tis our humour to admire the more where we expect the leſs. The cauſe then of thy Love is either from Beauty or Virtue; if from Beauty, how wilt thou love her when ſhe is old? If from Virtue, why doſt thou covet to lie with her? there needs not that low act of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to the high Communion of Virtues; and I ſhould ſcarce take thee for a Platonic Lover, to warm a bed with her. But ſhall I tell thee the cauſe? don't be afraid of truth then; thou firſt lov'ſt her to ſatisfie thy Luſt; and if thou after
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49622:6"/>continue to lie with her, 'tis either for want of a better, or 'cauſe thou canſt not be rid of her. For I look on all the Perfections in females but as ſo many Encouragements to deſire; and that the beſt of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men like the beſt of Sallads, procure the ſtrongeſt appetite; and in truth 'tis the woman is affected, not this, the Sex being the ſubſtance, and the Miſtris but the ſhadow; or that the Rule of thy affection, and this the Inſtance. But then thou wilt be goring of me with that common goad of objection, thy ſo much curioſity in choice, and rather my Lady than <hi>Jone.</hi> Prethee tell me, be thy appetite never ſo good, do's thy meat reliſh the worſe for being the cleanlier dreſt? I never knew that good cookery did turn the edge of a good ſtomach; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if thou limiteſt thy fanſie to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49622:7"/>one diſh, thou hadſt need to be both long in chuſing and neat in dreſſing, as well to avoid nauſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as to continue provocation. Remember that <hi>July</hi> holds not all the year, nor youth all thy life, there is a <hi>December</hi> and Winter of age that attends on both; and that Paſſion that in its Spring will take fire at any face, will in its Autumn be froſt at all; a bed-ridden palat is ſcarce ſenſible of ſauce, much leſs meat; not the beſt of weapons, how brisk and keen ſoever at the firſt, but after long uſing grows dull, and requires a whetting: ſo that this ſtudious culling of bed-fellows, argues but the ſerious contemplations of mortality, and is no more than a wiſe proviſion for futurity. Where, <hi>Frank,</hi> is your Love then? Call'ſt thou that Love that ebbs and flows with the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49622:7"/>bloud? that is the brat of a goatiſh humor, merely ſervient to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and often dead before it? No, the Eſſence of that Paſſion is as pure and laſting as the Soul it waits on; a ſacred Veſtal flame, perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually torrid and unextinguiſhable; 'tis thy under-girdle Love that's mortal, of flames groſs and tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, which moving in a region lower than thy heart, prove rather flaſhes than ſteady fires. I know thou art no ſtranger to multitude of examples that have been hotter than <hi>Italians</hi> in the chaſe of their games, and more frozen than <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> after the taking it, that in the ſame year have been ready to die of contraries, both Love and Hate; and with the ſame eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſtudied both a Marriage and Divorce; that have not more long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to obtein than having obteined,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49622:8"/>to deſert their hopes, and their Loves periſh'd together, the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one the expiration of the other. But may be thou wilt add to thy other motive, that of Wealth, ſhe's rich. Nay now I hear thee, and do ſo far allow thee to court the Lady for her Fortune, as I would the Chamber-maid for her Miſtris; but have a care of loving in earneſt, or letting in of Love farther than thy Tongue; a ſigh or two in the preſence if thou wilt, but no ejaculations in private; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a difference betwixt acting and ſuffering a Paſſion; be nothing the ſadder, though nothing the richer; like a good Soldier riſe not ſo repulſt from one Leaguer, but to retein ſtrength enough preſently for another, that in a while thy ſoul will become face-proof, the later beauty the pellet of the former,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49622:8"/>till variety give the maſtery to thy judgment, and make thee a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Servant, but no particular Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. But thou wilt juſtifie yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; thou haſt a fortune of thine own, and the weightineſs of that requires a partner in the managing it. I don't gainſay it; nay I am ſo much of thy ſide, that I think a wife in no caſe more allowable, than either for the getting or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of an Eſtate. As for thy Love-marrying, I reckon it both the paradiſe and purgatory of fools. But yet this, <hi>Frank,</hi> is only an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology for a wife, not love, and think me no enemy to marriage, but to the fondneſs of thy deſire; I would have thee get a wife, but not to loſe thy ſelf; to ſerve thy occaſions, but to maſter thy paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſo to love with reaſon, as not to woe without ſenſe. Credit me,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49622:9"/>I do not at all think it to ſavour of impoſſibility, ſeriouſly to court and marry too, and yet unſing'd by any ſpark of Love, though I cannot but acknowledge the temptations of the other Sex; for I reckon them amongſt their Studies: yet that Reaſon, or the Soul and Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry of Man ſhould be baſely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted to them, I ſhould as ſoon believe an Eagle to ſtoop at Flies, or Divinity at Toys. I conceive, <hi>Frank,</hi> the neceſſity of thy marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtreightens not thy judgment to this one Lady; I would have thee to look on her as not without companions, and then if thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt an unlucky caſt of it, thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune will have this comfort, thou art no loſer, though no winner. Prethee why ſhould not a Woman be view'd with as little ardour as an handſom Statue? or what is the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49622:9"/>influence of Fleſh, as to the eye, above that of Marble? If thou comeſt into a ſpacious Gallery va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly behung, thou canſt walk it round, look on this Picture and like it, then turn thy face and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it in the beauty of another; there needing no more to the aſpect of a face than of imagery, but only the complacency of the Beholder, and the commendation of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. Women are a kind of Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique too: If thou comeſt to a ſhop, ſeeſt a commodity and likeſt it, thou cheapen'ſt it; if thou bargaineſt, thou takeſt it; if not, to the next ſtanding, the Market's full and free. I tell thee tis an Injury no leſs to Nature than Reaſon, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pale all perfection within the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of one creature. Now after all this, do I expect thou ſhouldſt bid me turn the Tables and play
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49622:10"/>my ſelf the queſtion, Was I never in Love? Troth, <hi>Frank,</hi> I cannot excuſe my ſelf from the vanities of youth, may be I have; but let me remember thee, I have had Rattles and Hobbi-horſes too in my days, but I have left them, and now look on them and thy thoughts with the ſame diſdain. That Mariner that hath ſcaped a rock, may be a Pilot to the next Paſſenger. 'Tis my faith now, that 'tis as poſſible to be ſick of the Plague a year, as of Love a day; and I doubt not, when time ſhall ripen both thy judgment and age, but thou wilt then ſit a moſt ſtrict judge upon thy ſelf, and think no cenſure too ſevere to thy preſent follies, or charity too boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful to the true advice of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thy true Friend, <hi>J.H.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49622:10"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>PRethee, dear Friend, do not burn <hi>Diana</hi>'s Temple only to be talked of: Modern <hi>wits</hi> (like ſpirits of the lower <hi>Region</hi>) once conjured up, muſt be ſet on work, though of miſchief. I muſt confeſs thou ventureſt hard on the <hi>parado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xology</hi> of thy brain, that dareſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Liſts <hi>Athanaſius</hi>-like, <hi>contra mundum;</hi> diſputing that with thy <hi>pen,</hi> which the world from <hi>Adam,</hi> and thy ſelf by thy practice proveſt <hi>undeniable.</hi> What is ſaid in caſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> a little <hi>Philoſophy</hi> makes men <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> but enough confirms them in the <hi>truth,</hi> is true of thee in point of <hi>love;</hi> of which and its objects thou art no more a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>Judge,</hi> than a <hi>Red-coat</hi> is of a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49622:11"/>Moot-caſe. Did I not know that all <hi>wonder</hi> proceeded of <hi>ignorance,</hi> and that people moſt admire what they leaſt underſtand, I ſhould wonder at thy wonder, that a man of thy <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>complexion,</hi> and born of a Mother, ſhould call that <hi>ſtumbling,</hi> which is ſo graceful and natural a <hi>motion;</hi> fall out with love and women, yet by thy own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, underſtand neither. Thou turn'ſt <hi>Andabate</hi> and fighteſt blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, not knowing againſt whom or for what. I prethee, Friend, what Countrey-Girl has ſlighted thy <hi>Madrigals,</hi> and diſentertained thy affections, that thou quarrel'ſt and fall'ſt at defiance with the whole Sex? He that ſaid all <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> were liers, was himſelf a <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian:</hi> and thou condemneſt all Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers as mad, yet art thy ſelf a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and conſequently mad, or elſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49622:11"/>more mad that thou art not a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. I never yet knew any deſpiſe <hi>Monarchy,</hi> but thoſe that could not be <hi>Monarchs.</hi> Every man in this is a <hi>Huntſman,</hi> who coming ſhort of the <hi>Hare,</hi> cries, <hi>Hang her, 'tis dry meat.</hi> Among the reſt of thy wonders, thou mayſt put this for one, that I who am unconcerned, ſhould at this diſtance take up the <hi>cudgels</hi> in defence of a friend, whom thou haſt laught into ſilence; but the Proverb excuſes me, <hi>He whom ſorrow makes dumb, deſerves double pity.</hi> For my part, I muſt confeſs I love to <hi>ſleep in a whole skin,</hi> and not to engage in anothers quarrel, unleſs he will lend me his <hi>skull</hi> to bear the blows: but this being the common cauſe, 'tis pity <hi>truth</hi> ſhould be out-worded, and her innocence be ſuſpected to want clearneſs, merely for want of clearing There
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49622:12"/>is no man more unfit for this work than I, having been ever as <hi>athei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical</hi> in Love as thy ſelf; and ſo far from being an <hi>Opponent</hi> to thy <hi>Theſis,</hi> that I have ever been a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Aſſertor</hi> of thy <hi>Doctrine,</hi> till <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience</hi> reformed my judgment, and makes me look on my former error with regret and diſdain. 'Tis ſo far from being a wonder to me, that one pleaſant, affable and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable, one that has view'd variety of <hi>beauties,</hi> ſhould fall in love with one <hi>woman,</hi> that I wonder how it could be otherwiſe; none being fitter for Love than one ſo qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor can any find a <hi>beſt,</hi> that have not view'd all. That <hi>Love per ſe</hi> is the ruine of its ſubject, I deny; yet I allow it may be <hi>accidentally</hi> true, and be a <hi>paſſion</hi> not the leſs noble. And as I would not have it only reſtrained to <hi>woman</hi> for its
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49622:12"/>object: ſo I would not have them totally excluded. And truly I am ſo far from believing that Sex not an object of love, that I can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admit of any beſides. That Love has ſeveral objects, as Heaven, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the reſt which you reckon up, with many more, I deny not. But all they, as <hi>oblique</hi> objects, are ſo far from being <hi>adequate,</hi> that they draw Love in ſeveral <hi>denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi> as <hi>piety, duty, friendſhip,</hi> &amp;c. And but that ſeriouſneſs would be thrown away on thee, and any thing here but <hi>ſophiſtry</hi> uſeleſs, I could tell thee from the learned, that <hi>Love</hi> is only an <hi>expanſion of the ſoul to its object;</hi> which is, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is <hi>attractive:</hi> and that natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>man</hi> loves himſelf beſt and firſt, and all other things in <hi>ſubordination</hi> to himſelf; and that whatever is moſt like <hi>man</hi> in nature and habit,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49622:13"/>is the propereſt <hi>object</hi> of his Love. Then 'twill follow (whether you will or no) that no object is ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as <hi>woman.</hi> But thou'lt laugh at theſe old-faſhion'd grounds, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them like <hi>Harry</hi>'s <hi>codpieces.</hi> To abſtract <hi>Love</hi> from <hi>ſenſuality</hi> in a natural ſenſe, is both impoſſible and needleſs, it deriving a greater influence from the ſenſitive ſoul, and being a Paſſion from which <hi>Brutes</hi> are not exempt. Nay that very thing which you call <hi>ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and will allow it to derive its <hi>legitimation</hi> only from an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, may ſhew an antienter <hi>coat</hi> than Ordinances, it being the only way chalked out by <hi>nature</hi> for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation and preſervation of every ſpecies. So that your <hi>Epithetes</hi> and <hi>Synonyma</hi>'s of concupiſcence and carnal appetite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I attribute to the luxuriance of your fanſie; and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49622:13"/>muſt tell you, we can eaſily give you &amp; your ways the like <hi>terms</hi> without the help of a <hi>Sylva.</hi> But your main <hi>heſitancy</hi> is, What are your <hi>cauſes</hi> of Love? 'Tis not bare <hi>red</hi> and <hi>white,</hi> that are either cauſes of, or colours for it, but the <hi>ſituation</hi> and <hi>contexture</hi> of both. I never loved my Miſtris face, becauſe fair, but becauſe I liked it, and thereby thought it ſo, and I therefore thought it ſo, becauſe <hi>hers:</hi> ſo that ſhould <hi>time</hi> or <hi>accident</hi> (from which no face has a Protection) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>complexion</hi> in the eye, I'd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein the ſame <hi>Idea</hi> ſtill in mine. Next, for the Gentlemans <hi>change</hi> (with which you upbraid him) much may be pleaded in excuſe: for beſides the great delight in <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety,</hi> I know no reaſon why, if a man find himſelf in an <hi>errour,</hi> he may not repent and take a new courſe. Nor may you call it <hi>prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49622:14"/>of affection; he that grounds his Love right is above uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in regard the true cauſe of Love, which is <hi>ſympathy,</hi> cannot periſh before its object. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſay, <hi>Beauty is a Chymaera, and every man a</hi> Pygmalion <hi>that carves to himſelf a Miſtris;</hi> will you from thence infer, that becauſe all men do not think one face <hi>beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> no man ſhould think any ſo? And I appeal to the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> whether for a Lover to chuſe his own Miſtris, and love her, or court her be a piece of <hi>ignorance</hi> or <hi>paganiſm.</hi> Nor can you deny that <hi>manners, carriage</hi> and <hi>virtue</hi> are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centives to Love; and that theſe things are really viſible in that Sex by any that look not through <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles</hi> of <hi>prejudice.</hi> But he that has an ill ſight diſlikes all objects. Thou haſt an <hi>humour</hi> in thine eyes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49622:14"/>whereby thou canſt not diſcern <hi>action</hi> from <hi>behaviour;</hi> I like it not the worſe if acquired; no more than I do a good <hi>Scholar</hi> that ſpeaks <hi>Latine</hi> by the <hi>Grammar.</hi> That there are <hi>arcana imperii</hi> among them, as well as us, is undeniable; for if all were as they appear, they would be rather <hi>angels</hi> than <hi>women.</hi> 'Tis true much <hi>action</hi> and <hi>deceptio viſus</hi> is in both ſexes in point of Courtſhip, whereby they <hi>recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> draw their expectations to an height <hi>unobteinable,</hi> and ſucceeding <hi>enjoyments</hi> convince both Sexes of a <hi>handſom</hi> (but commonly an <hi>equal) cheat.</hi> I ſhall not only allow of that Doctors charity, that held, <hi>That 'tis poſſible ſome virtue may be found in ſome women:</hi> but alſo ſhall experimentally add, <hi>That much vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue may be found in many.</hi> 'Tis not for nothing that all virtues are <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49622:15"/>by <hi>Grammarians</hi> with <hi>haec,</hi> and fanſied by Painters in <hi>female</hi> ſhadows. Virtues are like Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds rare and ſmall; nor ſhould we eſteem them were they to be bought by the pound. I take <hi>virtue</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> to be cauſes of affection; but I mean not by beauty the mere <hi>ſuperficies</hi> of a viſage, but the <hi>ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry</hi> of parts; and he that grounds his affection rightly on that, finds a becoming <hi>beauty</hi> even in old <hi>Age. Virtue</hi> alſo I conceive a cauſe of <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>love</hi> a <hi>motive</hi> of <hi>copulation.</hi> Nor is generation for the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of virtues, but <hi>propagation</hi> of <hi>iſſue;</hi> ſince 'tis an undoubted <hi>law</hi> of <hi>nature,</hi> that all creatures deſire and endeavour <hi>perpetuation.</hi> You call <hi>luſt</hi> the cauſe of <hi>love;</hi> 'tis true, if you take all <hi>altitudes</hi> by your own <hi>Jacob</hi>'s ſtaff, 'tis ſo to you: ſo the <hi>Wolf</hi> conceives all creatures to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49622:15"/>eat <hi>raw fleſh,</hi> becauſe he does. I cannot imagin ſuch a <hi>Stocial apathy</hi> in men, unleſs in <hi>Eutopia,</hi> but that we do and may make that which you call <hi>luſt</hi> a part of <hi>love.</hi> Nor is that Paſſion itſelf blameable, but <hi>circumſtances</hi> may make it ſo: for the <hi>Stoies</hi> themſelves got children, and did not deny the being of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires in men, but their domineering over Reaſon. Nor is it the work of a <hi>wiſe</hi> man to be without <hi>paſſions,</hi> but above them. Conſider man as with a ſoul compounded of Will and Reaſon, the conqueſt of the <hi>will</hi> in this life can be but by <hi>ſynec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doche;</hi> which being conſidered, it will follow, That men abſtracted from deſires of this nature, are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be <hi>looked</hi> for, than <hi>found.</hi> And for your <hi>erratical Love,</hi> that is ſo planetary and unfixed, it ſhews its own weakneſs, but not your
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49622:16"/>ſtrength; though it be peripareti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, it makes not you a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher; ſince <hi>Love,</hi> like <hi>Sun-beams,</hi> being diffuſed, are but faint: but contracted to one object, are fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and calefactory. <hi>Wives</hi> are not <hi>Quelque choſes,</hi> in whom only <hi>variety</hi> breeds delight, but are ſolid food which never nauſeate ſound ſtomachs. For a man to love Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue abſtracted from its ſubject, is to fanſie a <hi>Chymaera;</hi> but Virtue in a woman is an undoubted <hi>motive.</hi> As to your ſimilitude of <hi>Joan and my Lady;</hi> take the whole Proverb, put in <hi>(in the dark)</hi> and you are anſwered. 'Tis not want of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, but due diſcerning; nor <hi>is</hi> ſhe as good, but <hi>ſeems</hi> ſo. The Cuckow once ſang better than the Nightingal; but remember who was Judge. Times ſwift motion and youths tranſitorineſs are <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49622:16"/>places</hi> in the beaten roads, where ever travelling <hi>wit</hi> baits and refreſhes himſelf in his <hi>pilgrimage.</hi> But yet <hi>deſires</hi> being part of the <hi>ſoul,</hi> and ſo immortal, do not decay in age, but only alter their motives and object. Nor is the world bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of examples of aged men, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly deſiring and performing rites of conjuncture with women. As for thoſe <hi>changeable</hi> and <hi>quick ſilver</hi> minds which <hi>love</hi> and <hi>loath</hi> in a moment, 'tis their Vice, and may give you this notion, <hi>That as their love can ſo ſoon and eaſily change into diſdain:</hi> ſo your preſent ſcorn may turn to a dotage on the like ground. And though perhaps you have not yet been in love, 'tis <hi>commune ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum</hi> (ſince you will call it ſo) like the Small-pox, <hi>every one hath been or muſt be troubled with it;</hi> and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies unacquainted with leſſer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49622:17"/>are irrecoverably ſwallowed up of greater. Your wary advice to your friend, <hi>to love with diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> I allow and commend; and for my part were I to love again, would not go a foot further than my <hi>counter-part</hi> ſhould meet me; but where I found real love, I would ſcorn to be out-vied, being of <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander</hi> his reſolution, <hi>No creature ſhould conquer me with love or hatred.</hi> 'Tis not good to play the Butcher with that naked Sex that have no Arms but to embrace with, nor Empiric-like, kill them by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale. I never yet met any of either Sex good at the ſport, but at laſt they met with a requital. 'Tis within the memory of man ſince a pregnant Spark furniſhed with two of your Cardinal Virtues, <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>diſdain,</hi> flung his <hi>fire-balls</hi> of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> on the whole Sex, courted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49622:17"/>ſome into <hi>dotage,</hi> and then <hi>jeer'd</hi> 'um; who at laſt fell foul on a Kitchin-wench, and doted, who repaid him with the ſame devices; and which was worſt, at laſt in deſpight married him. <hi>Homicida</hi> is of both Genders, and belongs to both Sexes. Your other points of marrying for wealth and yoke-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, I ſhall agree to with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. But I would not make wealth my Miſtris's Maſter, while <hi>woman</hi> ſtands by like the <hi>Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid</hi> with a <hi>broom</hi> to attend her. Let my Miſtris be a <hi>figure,</hi> and her portion the <hi>cyphers,</hi> which added to her, advance her much, but of themſelves ſignifie nothing. <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Courtſhip</hi> ſhould, but cannot be avoided by all; every one is not <hi>Hercules:</hi> but diſſimulation may and muſt be ſhun'd by all. There is no Soldier beleaguers a Gariſon,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49622:18"/>but with hopes to come off <hi>untouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> no Lover attempts a Miſtris, but hopes for fruition without <hi>bloudſhed;</hi> yet the Soldier may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a <hi>ſhot,</hi> and the Woer a <hi>repulſe;</hi> and that which he intends for a ſin, oft proves a puniſhment. He that lives a <hi>Catholic</hi> Woer, may at laſt come to the <hi>Purgatory</hi> of a general contempt. But methinks, Friend, you wheel about and approve that which at firſt you decried; there might be ſome hopes of agreement and <hi>band ſhaking</hi> between us. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>love</hi> and <hi>marriage,</hi> and I will join with thee againſt dotage; and would have Love ſequeſtred from dotage, as much as thy mind from this <hi>obſtinacy.</hi> But I ſee the Devil has always a cloven foot; you would now allow of <hi>Marriage</hi> without <hi>Love,</hi> and confound love and dotage as if the ſame. To wed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49622:18"/>without Love, is to be tied by the loins like a <hi>Monkey</hi> to a <hi>bed-poſt,</hi> neither is it poſſible to court or marry without love, as you write, for that want of love turns court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to <hi>flattery,</hi> and marriage to a <hi>bargain.</hi> That Women are Natures <hi>Errata,</hi> with <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and that they ſtudy tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is undoubtedly true; but yet that they do it not alone, your own example proves; who by this fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Anti-womaniſm</hi> tempt the ſex ſo much, that I could wiſh my ſelf one to dote on thee. Do not call the lawful and neceſſary <hi>intermix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of both Sexes to be a baſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Reaſon, Soul and Gallantry of a Man; 'tis ſo falſe and groundleſs, it deſerves no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer but the <hi>lie.</hi> Let thy friend alone with his choice, and if he think her ſo, ſhe is <hi>peerleſs;</hi> only
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49622:19"/>I admit your caution, <hi>While he ſeeks to win her, let him not loſe himſelf; nor ſhoot away all his ſhot at one volley, but keep a reſerve for a freſh encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> tis but diſcretion. And now to anſwer your ſimilitudinary Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Why a woman cannot be viewed with as little ardour as a Statute? it is <hi>becauſe a Statue is not a Woman, nor directly like a Woman;</hi> if it could be, <hi>Pygmalion</hi> will tell you there may be like affection, nor is the influence different as to the eye, but the power that actuates it; if a man view a thouſand Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, he generally likes one beſt, and having peruſed all, returns to that; and though the Market be free, and Wares various, a good Chapman ſticks to what he beſt fanſies, and deals in it. Neither is all perfection thereby impaled in one Creature; but there may be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49622:19"/>enough ſuppoſed in one, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent one. <hi>That your ſelf hath ever loved,</hi> I queſtion; but that you have <hi>fanſied</hi> and <hi>miſt,</hi> may be true; but you cannot thereby go out a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent <hi>Tutor.</hi> Nor ſhould I ever take that <hi>Mariner</hi> for my Pilot, who hath no other experience than <hi>ſplitting his own Ship:</hi> firſt guide your own <hi>Veſſel</hi> to the <hi>Port,</hi> before you take another to your manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſteerage. What it is to be ſick of Love or the Plague, you know much alike, and ſo ſhall be believed, having ſtudied both but in ſhape; for my part, I have known many ſick of Love, and yet reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; but the Plague I have no skill in. My deſire is, that you participate of your own <hi>counſel;</hi> ſuſpend your ſevere cenſure to your friend, and ſit firſt a ſtrict Judge on your ſelf, till <hi>time</hi> and <hi>experience</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49622:20"/>ripen your judgment and change your mind. Which I hope I ſhall not longer expect, than until you have ſeriouſly peruſed and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the experimental directions and wholſom advice of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thine, and thy Friends Friend, <hi>A.B.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49622:20"/>
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>IT is ſaid concerning <hi>Diogenes,</hi> that he enjoyned his friends, that ſhould be concerned about the manner of his interment, to bury him in a prone poſture, that when the world ſhould be turned upſide down, he might remain in a more decent and the uſual ſituation, with his face upwards. One would think that this converſion is either now adays approaching, or has lately ſuffered it, if we conſider how much we are overgrown with a new Generation of men, (the Wits of the Age) who by their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and humours not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to oppoſe and deride the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive manners and well digeſted Principles of their Anceſtors; but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49622:21"/>have of late planted their ſquirting and airy Wits to bedaſh the ſacred ſtate of Wedlock, that if poſſible they might unpeople the world, and uſher in its expiration with their own deceaſe, as if conſcious to themſelves of the vitiouſneſs of thoſe principles they have imbibed and the public miſcarriages they are guilty of, endeavour to obſtruct a ſurviving poſterity, that would pity their ignorance and explode their examples.</p>
               <p>It is now the Opinion of thoſe who pretend to underſtand moſt, that the world has been fool'd in nothing more than in an idle and tame ſubmitting to the Fetters of Marriage; that ſome one unknown to them did moſt injuriouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave ſo many Generations with this dull inſtitution, which did upon that account loſe the freedom
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49622:21"/>and vigour of generous actions, and miſcarried in thoſe Eſſays that would have ſhewn a greater Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Glory of mind, but when we ſhall find that the world has not received greater Benefits by the Idolaters of Liberty, than from the Votaries of Wedlock, we ſhall be able to return ſo criminable a charge.</p>
               <p>The higheſt wiſdom took the proſpect of all the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed what was the benefit and good of all, and not what might pleaſe the humour of ſome, who ſtarting up in particular generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and making a noiſe amongſt thoſe whom they lived, could yet with no juſtice reproach the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that governed their fathers; with which they are diſpleaſed through the capriciouſneſs of their own folly, and not the defect of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49622:22"/>precept, which like Beds and Couches are not to be accuſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are uneaſie to the ſick and diſtempered. This inſtitution like power ows its glory to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is paid it, whilſt every thing that is neglected, is by that ſcorn rendred cheap and contemptible: and any diſeſteem Marriage lies under, is not from the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are found in it, but only ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from the incivility of thoſe times that forbear to reſpect it. If perſons would ſtudy to do it juſtice, we ſhould find it again with the ſame Votaries about it; and not like dethron'd Monarchs without its ſtate and unattended. Marriage laid the foundation and firſt principle of civil ſociety, it was a yoak for which the neck of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence was not too ſoft and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and a condition governed by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49622:22"/>unerring virtue had yet need of theſe Allotments, as to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages and improvements of ſociety, and that which Marriage appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated was the firſt proclaming of <hi>Mine</hi> and <hi>Thine</hi> The earth was common, and the enjoyments of it had an undiſtinguiſh'd right, whilſt the concernments of the bed were ſacred and ſeparate; in all things elſe, we can allow a ſharer but in the Intereſts of our Love. To oblige Mankind by an obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſacred and unaltered to the affairs and intereſts of one Love, was an act of that prudence and wiſdom againſt which none can diſpute. We can with no equity raiſe a title to more, ſince the Law of Nature proclames that loving of one ſhould be for enough, and that ſex muſt have been left in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition wholly baſe and mercenary,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49622:23"/>to have took the pay of every A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. There would have been ſet up a Tyranny in Love, which muſt have been the moſt cruel and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable of others, becauſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd on the beſt intereſts of life. The force of conqueſt had been a ſufficient title to the objects we had coveted: But Marriage puts the world into Diſcipline and a happy Government, incloſing the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon injoyment that none might lay claim to the portion of another. Had beauty and the poſſeſſion of that Sex been left a prey to the Conqueror, and ſubject to be born away by the moſt forcible Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips: Mankind muſt have ever dwelt jealous of each other, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claming an enmity againſt all the world, and have judged their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er alone a ſufficient defence; But by the force of Matrimonial Laws
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49622:23"/>and the Allotments made us from above, we live in quiet and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with each other, who muſt elſe have ſtood perpetually on our guard, and ſecured what we had loved from the wandring luſts of others. The world muſt have been perpetually involved in quarrels, ſince Love is more reſtleſs and more impatient than Ambition, and whilſt a charming object had many claimers, ſhe muſt at laſt have yielded to the conqueror, and not have gratified the Paſſion of the moſt deſerving, but the moſt happy, being without the exerciſe of that Empire which Halcyon laws had gave her, that muſt have been wholly loſt amidſt the animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of Rivals. But ſince Love is preſerved in theſe bounds, its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies and advantages remain to the world, its childiſh and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49622:24"/>troubleſom qualities are cut off by Laws, its made tame and gentle, which would elſe have devoured the faireſt concernments of the Univerſe, ſince the Love it cuts off and regulates, it could not have born, and the Love it manages it cannot ſpare.</p>
               <p>But why this condition is deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo contemptible, and dreaded by the Libertines of our times, is by reaſon of that ſevere cenſure they harbour of it, to be as full of Plagues as <hi>Pandora</hi>'s Box, no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhall we admit of it, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently find our ſelves to be fettered with cares and perplexities; and therefore celebrate a ſingle life for its freedom and repoſe. But let me ask them, who found in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſtate that tranquillity they have pretended to admire; what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Life is there that is always
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49622:24"/>ſerene, quiet and undiſturb'd? and although cares may attend that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate more than other conditions; yet thoſe Advantages and Bleſſings, thoſe ſweet ſocieties which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from it, are able to ſweeten its croſſes, eaſe its burdens, and retrieve whatever is deemed tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. And although they can ſhew us the life of ſome rude and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Philoſopher, who in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirements lockt up from the world, and <hi>Vatia</hi>-like lies buried in a drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Idleneſs, boaſteth of quiet and repoſe. We can ſhew them many examples of virtuous men, living not only contentedly, but admired in the eyes of Matrimony, ſpreading their uſeful qualities as well as iſſues, whilſt the Stoic has permitted his virtue to droop and wither in the ſhade of his own humor. An excellent perſon may
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49622:25"/>do much for the world with his own ſufficiency, but he doubly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges it, who in a Seminary of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro's is continually propitious to it, and by the force of embraces cauſes lives to thoſe Generations which ſtand next the worlds laſt calenture and burning fit. <hi>Pompey</hi> did not only fight himſelf for the Liberty of <hi>Rome,</hi> till he was its greateſt and mightieſt ſacrifice, but left alſo thoſe gallant ſons who bravely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to revive it when faint and dying. We ſhine with a ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary virtue without the irradiations of an Off-ſpring, and beſide it lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth its luſtre and ſtrength, when it is obliged to wander in various enterteinments. How had the world ſuffered, if a perſon who by many generous actions became the dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Mankind, neglecting to tranſinit a copy from ſo beloved
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49622:25"/>and glorious an Original, had ſet at once in his being and his race. In antient wars infants have been carried to encourage battels, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by with their unactive bloud ſtrangely animating the veins of others, and it hath moreover been found to work much upon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of human nature, a kind of gallant affection for the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſome glorious perſon left to the guidance of a tender hand. Such efforts ſerved the race of the <hi>African</hi> and the <hi>Gothic</hi> Hero, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing to the world this belief and benefit together, that he which leaves his virtue an orphan, may have erected for it the Hoſpitals of ſtately tombs and the Panegyrics of hiſtory; but he that would have it laſting and uſeful, as well as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, muſt leave it to his Iſſue, where in the active torrent of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49622:26"/>performances, it may accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulate the ſame glory and eſteem it found in the days of an anceſtor. To be only admired is a barren ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; to be uſeful and to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, is what the truly noble ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther covet, which is found in the virtues and good offices of our race. Neither ſhall we find any men of a more noble gallantry as amongſt thoſe <hi>duo fulmina belli,</hi> I mean <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Brutus,</hi> men not only religiouſly prizing the married ſtate, but ſuch as were bleſſed with the ſociety of thoſe women, that for the returns of love and kindneſs were famous in every generation. We chuſe friendſhip as a field for virtue to reap advantages in; and none but retired and treacherous natures will be without the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of that. But without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion that friendſhip is the nobleſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49622:26"/>bound in the ſureſt Ligaments that is commenced in Marriage, than any took up on other ſcores. No nation could have flouriſhed nor have been ſucceſsful in its affairs, if a wanton flame had conſum'd the manly temper and vigour of youth, or if their Paſſions had not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported them to ſuch violent acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet the gentleſt concernments of thoſe flames, incenſing the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities and jealouſies of rivalſhip, the prodigality of amorous addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, had diſlodged all Braveries of mind, and baffled all thoſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages with which they ſhould have ſerved their Generations. And therefore all wiſe and prudent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments knew they ſhould have but little order and leſs of induſtry, where the affairs of an idle paſſion poſſeſſed the hearts and heads of their Subjects. Marriage gives the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49622:27"/>thoughts a home, and hereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the inconſtant and flitting fanſie is directed to an aim, and kept ſtedfaſt by a peculiar authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that would elſe be captivated by the wandring luſts of ſtews and concubines: And who does not (that is bias'd by reaſon) take more pleaſure in managing the intereſts of a family, and a laſting name by an happy iſſue, than in cheriſhing a ſhort-liv'd inclination? The want of a juſt intereſt to manage has brought in thoſe Inconveniences that are found in the world; and that pleaſantneſs and gayneſs, which is childiſhly called, good humor, ſo much idolized in the ſingle life, what is it but a trifling and ſtrange impertinence, a thing without all conduct and prudence; and after the follies of youth are over, even inſupportable to thoſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49622:27"/>who have the moſt admired it. What Judgment can we paſs on this, any otherwiſe than that they laviſhly ſpend the prudent ſtock of nature, which becoming bankrupt by exceſſive practices, they are after forced to yield to thoſe humors, which ſpeak the wants and pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of nature, which deſigned no man to that vanity, as to be taken up with the contemplation of his own endowments, like the fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic Youth, who made Love to, and died for it himſelf. He that gathers the ſtock of his own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, into his own breaſt and keeps them there like roſes that grow in deſerts, he dies uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and unenjoy'd. Virtue is diffuſive and loves occaſions to exerciſe its vivacy and vigor, what we carry about us ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that we were not deſigned
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49622:28"/>to be happy alone, whilſt both the ſolace of the mind, and an endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed life conſiſt in an union with ſomething different.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter to a Friend, delivering an Opinion of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Riſing.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat you may receive an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Scotch</hi> buſineſs, and that there hath been ſuch irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute alteration about the <hi>Treaties</hi> lately, 'tis fit you know this <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern</hi> ſtorm, like a new diſeaſe hath ſo far poſed the <hi>Doctors</hi> of State, that as yet they have not given it a name; though perchance they all firmly believe it to be <hi>rebellion;</hi> and therefore, Sir, it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if theſe do here as the learned
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49622:28"/>in <hi>Phyſic,</hi> who when they know not certainly the grief<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, preſcribe Medicines ſometimes too ſtrong, ſometimes too weak. The truth is, we here judge concerning the <hi>Scotch</hi> affairs much after the rate as <hi>Mortals</hi> do of the <hi>Moon;</hi> the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple think it no bigger than a buſhel, and ſome likewiſe think it a vaſt world with ſtrange things undiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in it; two ill ways of caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it up; ſure the firſt will make us too <hi>ſecure,</hi> the other too <hi>fearful.</hi> I confeſs I know not how to write in the <hi>middle,</hi> and ſet it right; nor do I think you know; ſince I ſhould believe the queſtion rather to be, A <hi>King</hi> or no <hi>King?</hi> then A <hi>Biſhop</hi> or no <hi>Biſhop?</hi> In great mutinies and inſurrections of this nature, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſpeciouſly conſcionable were never wanting, and indeed they are neceſſary; for <hi>rebellion</hi> is of itſelf ſo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49622:29"/>ugly, that did it not put on the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of <hi>Religion,</hi> it would <hi>affright</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>draw</hi> people unto it; and being <hi>drawn,</hi> could not <hi>hold</hi> them without it. <hi>Imaginary cords</hi> that ſeem to faſten man to heaven, have tied things here below faſter than any other obligation. If it be <hi>liberty of conſcience</hi> they ask; it is a fooliſh requeſt, ſeeing they have it already, and muſt have in deſpite of power. For as <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Jews, Nemo cogitur credere invitus.</hi> If they exerciſe that <hi>liberty,</hi> 'tis dangerous; for not three men are of the ſame <hi>opinion</hi> in all; and then each family muſt have a war within itſelf. Look upon the long preparations, and conſider withal that <hi>Propheſies are ceaſed,</hi> and therefore they could not foretell this <hi>Book</hi> ſhould be ſent to them, &amp; you will conclude they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imploy'd <hi>conſcience,</hi> than <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:49622:29"/>them. Inquire after the <hi>leaders,</hi> and you'l hardly find them <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or men of ſo high ſanctity, that they ſhould order <hi>Religion; Leſley</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf if his ſore were ſearcht, would certainly be found one, who becauſe he could not live well there, took up a trade of <hi>killing men</hi> abroad; and now is return'd to <hi>kill</hi> men at home. If you will have my <hi>opinion,</hi> I think their quarrel to the <hi>King</hi> is the ſame they have to the <hi>Sun,</hi> that he doth not warm them ſo much, nor viſit them ſo oft as he doth others. <hi>God</hi> and <hi>nature</hi> plac'd 'um in the ſhade, and they are angry with the <hi>King</hi> for it. To conclude, this is the <hi>caſe;</hi> the great and wiſe Husband-man hath plac'd theſe <hi>beaſts</hi> in out-fields, and they would needs break <hi>hedges</hi> to come into the <hi>Garden.</hi> This is the belief of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours <hi>J.S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="characters">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:49622:30"/>
            <head>CHARACTERS.</head>
            <div type="character">
               <head>A Whore</head>
               <p>IS one of <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes that carries fire in the tail, to deſtroy the ſtanding corn. She goes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of a decayed Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman; and indeed ſhe is gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle enough, a Half-Crown will make her come to hand. The Devil and ſhe are co partners in undoing, for one ſpoils the body, the other the ſoul. Turn-up ſhe affects above all roots in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. She cares not for the <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> having lain often at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Ward. Her walk is <hi>Covent-Garden;</hi> and her Exchange a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern. He that goes to ſalute her,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49622:30"/>is deceived, for ſhe is very coy of her lips, and therefore bulwarks them about with paint. Her breath ſtinks worſe than a Bear-garden; her furniture conſiſts of a Plaiſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>box, a Periwig, and a Looking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs; beſides a Pimp, which ſhe accounts one of her neceſſary im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements. She is a ſhe-<hi>Bias,</hi> and can ſay, <hi>Omnia mea mecum porto.</hi> She is a preſervative againſt a hard froſt; and a Regiment of them will beggar <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> for they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fire about them. Her children, if any, are like wind-falls, and found in the Kings high-way. She is not ambitious, but delights in fallings; yet by her falling her Stallions riſe. She is a hackney Jade, and lets every fool ride her; a Barbers chair, as ſoon as one is out, another is in. She is a very Butcher, and ſells her fleſh by the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49622:31"/>ſtone; one may buy her awhole at the price of damnation. She is like a Medlar, never ripe till rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; like Camomile, ſhe thrives the better the more ſhe is trod. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thirty ſhe is in her Zenith, and then from thence ſhe declines; for the pox or rotten teeth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will write her ſtale or ugly, and trading will decay; and then her only preferment is the degree of a Baud, where three Strong-water Bottles, an ounce of Tobacco, and two Countrey-Wenches ſets her up; and ſhe drives a trade till <hi>Shrove-Tueſday;</hi> and a Cart and a bunch of Turnips are the reward of her labours; and the <hi>Bridewell</hi> the limbo of both body and bones.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:49622:31"/>
               <head>A Patentee</head>
               <p>WAs ſometimes a Gentleman of Fortunes, but being caſt over-board by his own riot or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, lays hold of the next thing he meets with. He is begot like a Mule, between a Courtier and a Citizen, but turns Parricide to both. No air nips him ſo much as a Weſt-wind coming from the Parliament-Houſe, for that brings him to the Falling-ſickneſs; the Re-public and his Re-private never are in conjunction; but like <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> when one ſets the other riſeth. He is an excellent Alchymiſt and can draw Gold out of Sope, Candles, Marrow bones, and what-not? Nothing angers him ſo much as the ſound of a Reformation;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49622:32"/>for then he is projecting to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a Patent to hang himſelf. Like a Louſe, he ſhrowds on the ſhoulders of Greatneſs; for that is his main protection. All honeſt men ſhun his company, and he theirs; in which regard you may call him a Separatiſt. His walk is <hi>Weſtminſter hall,</hi> or the <hi>Court,</hi> with his hand-full of Papers, becauſe he would be taken for a man of note. The Monopoliſt and he like <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> twins, both live and die to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. In his chamber his Glaſs and he are in a deep conſultation, how to ſet his face that it may go even with the times; like a Watch, whereof his tongue is the Alarm. His pretences are fair for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and eaſe of the Subject; To reform ſome grievance (meaning his own poverty,) to increaſe Trade (meaning of Patentees,) and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49622:32"/>diſorders; to which he rather adds a ſail than a ballaſt. He has little skill in the Law, but only in the penal Statutes, and that in a defenſive way to play the knave in a circle, and yet keep out of their bounds to prevent hanging; and leſs in the Goſpel, unleſs to fiſh by <hi>Peter</hi>'s example, for ſuch fiſh as have money in their mouths. His Religion is commonly but skin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deep, it may appear in his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but it never comes near his heart; 'tis writ upon changeable Taffata, for good and lawful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations; his Religion and his Practice make him like the new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Pictures, one way an Angel, another way a Devil. All his life is a continued <hi>Cataline</hi>'s Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; he and the Common-wealth are like two feet, if one riſe, the other falls; if both chance to riſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49622:33"/>together, 'tis but a leap, that the fall may be the greater. He feeds upon new Projects; his drink is the tears of the poor Labourers; and commonly his Livery is the ruine of ſome Corporation. His diſeaſe lies in his ears, for he is commonly infected with a Pillory, which at laſt comes into his neck, and <hi>Tiburn</hi> ends him; where his only glory is, that he died for the Commonwealths good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:49622:33"/>
               <head>A Politic</head>
               <p>IS one that makes Heaven bow to Earth; he placeth his <hi>ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum bonum</hi> in Earths felicity, and depends on no other Providence but the reach of his own brain. His Religion is but the viſor of his policy; and whatever virtue he has, craft is the keeper of it. His looks are candid, and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie is the only Saint he adores. All his diſcourſes are obſcure and ambiguous; like the Devils in the <hi>Delphic</hi> Oracle; you may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the words, but not the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. He is like an Aſpen-Tree, every wind of greatneſs blows him and he bends. Is his Prince va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous? he is daring; covetous? he is ſparing; laſcivious? he is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49622:34"/>wanton; religious? he pretends much; his heart is a Theatre, wherein all humors are preſented, and his face pantomimical. He is of that mans Religion, with whom he talks; a <hi>Caeſarean,</hi> a <hi>Pompeian,</hi> which ſoever prevails; he'l cry, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p with them,</hi> and <hi>Down with them</hi> all in a breath. Like a Waterman he looks one way and rows ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; or like a Lapwing, keeps moſt noiſe when ſhe is fartheſt from her neſt; or a cunning Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, that ſeldom makes a blow without a falſifie; fuller of Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons than Anſwers, rather deſiring to know anothers ſecrets, than bewray his own. Pleaſures he is not much delighted in, but only like the Dog at <hi>Nilus,</hi> laps as he runs, for fear of the Crocodile. Every one that he deals with, he ſuppoſeth hath the Maſter-reach
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49622:34"/>in cunning; and therefore ſtill car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries both eyes open. His ſight is ſtrong enough to apprehend dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in <hi>Embrio,</hi> and ſo quells them before ſhape or form make them terrible. If a Contract blow fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably, he hoiſeth ſails, and with it ſteers his Voyage; if a croſs gale comes to his main under-ground Deſign, he thruſts out the Oars of fair Pretences through the Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holes of his conſcience. He would be accounted every mans friend, that he might know his ſecrets. All his actions are tipped with fair Pretences, yet are directed to himſelf, and therefore looks no higher. Whatever his Theme be, his Application is his own ends: yet he is often contented to do any cheap courteſies; and makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf very joyful and happy in an opportunity, ſo as he be ſure to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49622:35"/>be no loſer by it. His cap and knee, his ſmiles and good words aee all at a minutes warning, to be dealt about on all occaſions. In a word, he is one that loves no man, but with a reſervation, nor will truſt any; nor indeed any wiſe man him, farther than he ſees him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>A Clubber</head>
               <p>IS a Hogs-head ſet on two ſtumps fit for no uſe but to hold Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor; the Tavern only is his <hi>ubi</hi> and the proper place of his reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; any other where he is like a Fiſh out of the water, who doth nothing but gape. He thinks Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture gave him a mouth, not to ſpeak, but to drink off his Liquor, for that is the main uſe he puts it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49622:35"/>to; he drinks not to live (as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture commands) but lives to drink. Of all the Miracles that ever Chriſt did, he thinks none ſo merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious for the ſalvation of his ſoul, as the turning water into Wine; and he in imitation can work a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle too; for he can turn a whole Shop of Wares into a Pint-pot. His only enquiry is, where dwells the beſt Sack or Claret? You ſhall find him and his Tribe about the declining part of the day, at rendezvous, like a Conſtellation fix'd in the lower Region of a known Tavern; where their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes appear like Comets, and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend drought; there they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated with a private Room, a half-Pint, ſome clean Pipes, and a Jordan. Their firſt Diſcourſe is a general Vote about the goodneſs of the Wine; the next pair of half-Pints
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49622:36"/>Pints produces News; where each puffs over the inſide of a Diurnal; but for want of that, the main Scene is, who were drunk the night before, and how they reel'd home. They are internally <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> and very exact in making clean the inſide of the Glaſs; their ſtricteſt Criticiſm is, <hi>Drink off your Cup.</hi> At laſt, when it ſtrikes twelve, they make a liquor'd Reckoning, drink their Wives Health, in whoſe defence they are dutifully drunk, till they loſe their own; and then they ſtagger home to bed, and find it in ſmall beer in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:49622:36"/>
               <head>A Politic Citizen</head>
               <p>IS a lump of <hi>combuſtible ignorance,</hi> whom the leaſt ſpark of news fires into a <hi>blaze</hi> of unlikely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures; he meaſures all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of forein News by the line of <hi>Stow</hi>'s <hi>Chronicle;</hi> which he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hears read, but out flies a piece of <hi>non-ſenſe,</hi> which he miſ-calls State-Policy, able to confound <hi>Machiavel.</hi> He much haunts the <hi>Poſt-Houſe</hi> to note into what forms men concoct their Faces at the reading of Letters; he frequents the <hi>Exchange</hi> in the <hi>poſt-meridian</hi> hours, becauſe then men empty themſelves of intelligence; his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly factorage is <hi>news,</hi> viewing a Bill of <hi>Exchange,</hi> he ſwears 'tis a <hi>Libel.</hi> Tell him of a <hi>Curranto</hi> and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49622:37"/>he's in heaven; he takes an <hi>Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack</hi> of foul weather for one of <hi>Merlin</hi>'s Propheſies. Upon hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Victory or loſs of a <hi>Sconce,</hi> he is enraged, and blames the State that he was not a <hi>General;</hi> he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tols the <hi>Low-Countrey's</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment above any <hi>Monarchy,</hi> becauſe the fat <hi>Citizens</hi> rule the roſt; he holds it impoſſible for the State ever to be ruined, becauſe it ſwims in <hi>Butter.</hi> His face is a piece of <hi>Stenography,</hi> where all <hi>Richelieu</hi>'s deſigns are writ in <hi>ſhort-hand.</hi> He keeps a <hi>common place</hi> book of hard State-words, which though he nor his <hi>Engliſh Dictionary</hi> underſtand, he after an <hi>Aldermans</hi> Plumb-broth Feaſt <hi>ſpues</hi> out among the learned Fraternity; and is therefore ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd with the name of a <hi>Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> and he turns <hi>Heretic</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves it; for they had rather ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49622:37"/>admire his ſpeeches, than go to the price of <hi>underſtanding</hi> them. All the paſſages he hears are <hi>Stratagems;</hi> if he hear but a Ballad, he ſinells <hi>Treaſon</hi> in it; he cannot endure <hi>Plays,</hi> becauſe there are <hi>Plots</hi> in them, ask him a queſtion, you undermine him; anſwer him with ſilence, he takes you for a <hi>State-Informer;</hi> he tells news by <hi>tale,</hi> not by <hi>weight.</hi> There is no way to ſtrike him dumb but drawing out your <hi>Table-Book;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man is a <hi>fool</hi> that is not of his <hi>opinion:</hi> but he takes him for an undoubted wiſe man that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauds his <hi>conjectures;</hi> he ſeldom approves any thing that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands, and yet he approves moſt things; he meditates on an old <hi>Manuſcript</hi> more than the <hi>Penta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuch;</hi> he wonders why the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyps</hi> is put in the end of the Bible,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49622:38"/>and thinks it a diſgrace; he takes <hi>Brightman</hi> for a better Interpreter than <hi>Daniel;</hi> he cuts the <hi>Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> out of his Bible, for fear of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; yet cannot tell why he hates it, but becauſe 'tis <hi>Apocrypha;</hi> and thinks <hi>Solomon</hi> but a fool in ſuffering his <hi>wiſdom</hi> to be put there. <hi>Monarchy</hi> he cannot abide, but ſays 'tis againſt <hi>Chriſtian Liberty;</hi> but thinks <hi>Anarchy</hi> is as old as the <hi>Chaos.</hi> He takes <hi>Malchus</hi>'s Servant to be a Saint, becauſe he had his ear cut; yet thinks him not right of his opinion, becauſe he had one left. He takes <hi>Peter</hi> for a Popiſh <hi>Biſhop,</hi> becauſe he cut off that ear. Where 'ere the Scripture ſays <hi>ſtrive,</hi> he takes it for <hi>fighting;</hi> that makes him ſo in love with <hi>Civil War.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Superiors he is <hi>dumb;</hi> to his inferiors <hi>deaf;</hi> the one he offends by <hi>ſilence,</hi> the other by <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:49622:38"/>to both he is <hi>ridiculous.</hi> In a word, he is the State <hi>Incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> the Cities <hi>bane,</hi> and Kings <hi>evil.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>A Schiſmatic</head>
               <p>IS one of thoſe raſh Servants that will not let the <hi>Wheat</hi> and the <hi>Tares</hi> grow together; but crops off his <hi>hair,</hi> or rather weeds it up, leſt it ſhould hinder the growth of his <hi>ears,</hi> that when the harveſt of <hi>tribulation</hi> comes, they may be reaped by handfuls <hi>for good conſiderations.</hi> He thinks it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be ſaved if ones hair tranſcends his teeth in longitude. He is in the head an <hi>Hermaphrodite,</hi> between a Frier and a Turc, the one ſhaves round the <hi>head,</hi> the other the <hi>crown,</hi> he both; he hopes
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49622:39"/>to be pulled up to Heaven by the <hi>ears</hi> like a <hi>pitcher.</hi> He is a Papiſt turn'd the wrong ſide outwards, and ſo ſtrongly denies their <hi>tenets,</hi> that he grants their <hi>maxims;</hi> his <hi>Religion</hi> and theirs run round in a circle till they meet. He is fallen out with <hi>Learning</hi> ſo, that he thinks <hi>ignorance</hi> his main <hi>ſaving grace;</hi> and would be content to ſpeak no Language but ſanctified <hi>Bulls,</hi> but that the Pope uſeth them; he ſtands much for <hi>Chriſtian Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> yet will tie all men from the uſe of <hi>ceremonies; Free-will</hi> he cries down in a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> yet mainteins that a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> may do what he pleaſe. All his Diſcourſe is the <hi>ſand</hi> of <hi>zeal</hi> bound together with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>lime</hi> of <hi>reaſon;</hi> for he calls that <hi>human Traditions,</hi> and proteſts the Brethren do not uſe it. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vex him more than to tell him, his ſoul is <hi>Gods Image,</hi> for he hates
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49622:39"/>
                  <hi>idolatry.</hi> To ſpeak <hi>languages,</hi> he ſays, is to glory in the confuſion of <hi>Babel;</hi> and to talk <hi>ſenſe</hi> is to advance <hi>carnal reaſon</hi> above the <hi>ſpirit.</hi> He wears his ſoul, as a <hi>Gallant</hi> that has put on his <hi>Periwig</hi> the back part formoſt; for whereas his <hi>will</hi> ſhould be <hi>judicious,</hi> his <hi>judgment</hi> is <hi>wilful.</hi> He flies <hi>human learning</hi> as a <hi>Serpent;</hi> three words of <hi>Latin</hi> will give him nine <hi>ſtools.</hi> His knowledg, how ſmall ſoever, never ſinks into his heart, but only ſwims in his <hi>brain;</hi> ſtanding bare at a <hi>Sermon</hi> makes his <hi>zeal</hi> catch cold, and that brings <hi>ſnuffling</hi> in the noſe. He is one of the <hi>Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys</hi> of <hi>Dovers</hi> Court; and can with more patience <hi>talk</hi> five hours, than <hi>hear</hi> one. In company he is excellent <hi>Phyſic;</hi> for he will either purge your <hi>gall</hi> with <hi>anger,</hi> or your <hi>ſpleen</hi> with <hi>laughter.</hi> Againſt every <hi>new meeting,</hi> he takes in ſtore
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49622:40"/>of <hi>new arguments</hi> to maintein ſome <hi>new-fangled</hi> opinion; which when he vents, his <hi>proſelytes</hi> are raviſh'd with <hi>admiration,</hi> and think him <hi>inſpired</hi> with ſtrange revelations, that he can ſpeak <hi>Engliſh</hi> and they not <hi>underſtand</hi> him. He will <hi>croſs</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> High-way rather than view a <hi>Croſs</hi> there. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was never ſo corrupted with <hi>Dutch</hi> Comments, as the Scripture is with his; his brain is like the <hi>pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> into which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Well diſchanels itſelf, and becomes ſtinking water. When he takes a <hi>Biſhop</hi> in his mouth, 'tis in that ſenſe as a <hi>Wolf</hi> takes a <hi>Lamb;</hi> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but <hi>ſimpliciter.</hi> Tell him of a <hi>High Commiſſion,</hi> and he holds his ears, and ſays there is a <hi>myſtery</hi> in that Poſture. Set but his <hi>zeal</hi> on fire, and it will flame, though it ſmother a Kingdom; the only
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49622:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>way to confute him is <hi>ſilence</hi> or <hi>laughter.</hi> He is all for <hi>Independent</hi> Church-Government, yet wiſhes all the <hi>Orthodox</hi> Clergy hang'd. He holds a <hi>Stable</hi> as holy as a <hi>Church;</hi> but holds a <hi>Chamber</hi> holier than both, if it be well furniſhed; that is, with a <hi>Bed</hi> and a <hi>Siſter;</hi> and then he cares not how long he <hi>ſtands.</hi> He that would draw the character of his <hi>Religion,</hi> had need have a Map of all the <hi>Earth</hi> and of <hi>Hell</hi> too, where his Principles are deeply rooted. He will not believe that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ever deſcended into <hi>Hell,</hi> but intends to take a Journey thither himſelf to diſpute with the <hi>Devil.</hi> There let him go for me.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:49622:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:49622:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:49622:42"/>
               <head>A Gallant</head>
               <p>IS one that Nature made while the World was in a <hi>Chaos,</hi> and therefore deteſts order <hi>ab origine.</hi> He dares uſe his <hi>tongue</hi> againſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but ſcarce his hands againſt a <hi>Butter-fly.</hi> Is he ſober? his care is how to be <hi>drunk,</hi> is he <hi>drunk?</hi> his next task is how to ſhift the <hi>rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning.</hi> All his diſcourſes are but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd with <hi>Oaths,</hi> which he uſes <hi>Euphoniae gratia.</hi> He has worn out all his friends, but the Hangman; and all his <hi>Apparel,</hi> but his <hi>Sword;</hi> which he hacks ſometimes againſt a <hi>Mantle-poſt,</hi> and ſwears he has been in a deſperate encounter; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from a <hi>Baudy-houſe,</hi> he ſwears he has been in hot ſervice, though his courage be ſoon taken down. Two <hi>French</hi> poſtures he has natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49622:42"/>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> to have his <hi>Flanks</hi> and his <hi>hair</hi> fall off, which laſt defect he ſupplies with the mercenary <hi>Auxiliaries,</hi> a <hi>Periwig.</hi> His face ſpeaks him no true Subject, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of its frequent <hi>riſings;</hi> to which Rebels his <hi>noſe</hi> is <hi>Standard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer,</hi> and carries the <hi>colours.</hi> His common Notion or <hi>Title-page</hi> is a <hi>Low-country Soldier;</hi> under which viſor he boaſts of Victories and Adventures which he heard diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of at the laſt Tavern. He ſets his <hi>faith</hi> to ſale, and cries, Who will give moſt? His <hi>Loyalty</hi> laſts no longer than his <hi>Money.</hi> His Threats are like <hi>Thunder-claps,</hi> or the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Mountains;</hi> and if a blow be brought forth 'tis like a <hi>mouſe;</hi> in the midſt of his fury, if you care not for his menaces, nor fear his blows, he will ſhake hands with you. 'Twere fearful if his <hi>valour</hi> were as great
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49622:43"/>as his <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> or if his <hi>power</hi> echoed his <hi>will.</hi> Though he be an <hi>Infidel</hi> himſelf, he would have others believe his Oaths when he promiſeth payment. You cannot do him a greater diſcourteſie, than to make his <hi>Chirurgeon</hi> drunk, for then he bewrays his <hi>ſecrets.</hi> He keeps good quarter with his <hi>Laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs,</hi> leſt ſhe ſhould diſcover the ſpots of his <hi>converſation.</hi> The firſt thing he does in the morning, is to bid a <hi>Pox</hi> take thoſe <hi>Fleas</hi> that bit him at night, which is ſure to be granted; and the laſt thing he doth at night, is to curſe the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ileman</hi> that <hi>cudgel'd</hi> him that day. In the morning, imitating the Sun immediately after his riſe, he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes into an <hi>Alehouſe;</hi> or if he can get one to ſpend for him, to a <hi>Tavern;</hi> ſo paſſes from <hi>ſign</hi> to <hi>ſign,</hi> through a whole <hi>Zodiac</hi> in a day,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49622:43"/>till he comes to <hi>Aquarius;</hi> and then goes by <hi>water</hi> to a <hi>Baudy-houſe,</hi> and comes out by <hi>fire.</hi> He believes there is no Sign of <hi>Virgo</hi> left in the World. In the end you ſhall find him kick'd by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions for having no Money a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, which he ſwears is in his other <hi>pockets,</hi> whenas he has but only one Suit, and that is thread-bare before the Tailor is paid. Thus when he has gone his <hi>round,</hi> and been <hi>abuſed</hi> by his Companions for abuſing them, he reels into the mouths of the <hi>Watch,</hi> and from thence is rowled into the <hi>Counter;</hi> where to his credit, many great Actions are imputed to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:49622:44"/>
               <head>A Ballad-maker</head>
               <p>IS a Volume of <hi>Rime</hi> compoſed by the hand of <hi>nonſenſe;</hi> or a <hi>muſical</hi> Inſtrument, not yet <hi>tun'd.</hi> An <hi>Ale-houſe</hi> he accounts the only <hi>Helicon;</hi> and the <hi>Ale-drapers</hi> Wife one of the nine <hi>Muſes.</hi> His <hi>wit</hi> runs thick or clear, like the <hi>Ale-barrel.</hi> He is a ſecond <hi>Charon;</hi> for none are wafted over by the way of <hi>Tiburn,</hi> but he receives money for their paſſage. He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly longs for blazing <hi>Stars,</hi> Earthquakes, Dearths, or ſtrange accidents. The <hi>Brethren</hi> keep con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant correſpondence with him, that he may compoſe their <hi>Libels</hi> into <hi>Metre;</hi> and being whipt or Pillory'd for it, he rejoiceth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he ſuffers for the <hi>truth.</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:49622:44"/>His Companions call him <hi>Poet</hi> at every word, but 'tis in a jeer; and being patient to bear all ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, believes it and bears it. Call him <hi>Gooſe</hi> or <hi>Woodcock,</hi> he is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged; but yet had rather eat your words than you ſhould. He is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of no Argument but <hi>beating;</hi> and that alone drives him out of your company. He is in pay by the Countrey Wenches, to write <hi>Love-Stories</hi> to lamentable <hi>Tunes;</hi> which they ſing to the <hi>Cows,</hi> and make them weep <hi>milky</hi> tears to hear them. His common Vaticans where his Books are preſerved, are the windows and walls of an <hi>Ale-Houſe</hi> in the Countrey. He like the Emblematiſts is beholden to an Engraver; but only his Wood-carver hath certain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Places; a <hi>man</hi> and a <hi>woman</hi> ſerve like <hi>Panpharmacons,</hi> for all
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49622:45"/>occaſions. He is a dutiful Son of the <hi>Church,</hi> and loves no innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Muſics;</hi> but they go like <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> to the Tune of the ſame. He is in no better <hi>cue</hi> to write a lamentable Story, than when he's <hi>Maudlin-drunk;</hi> his brain is the common-ſewer of <hi>Poetry;</hi> the ſtreams which he ſucks from <hi>Poets,</hi> he defiles with the muddy ſtinking puddles of his Additions. There is many a man is made a <hi>Martyr</hi> by his Elegies; wherein his <hi>Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtics</hi> perſecute the very aſhes, and <hi>hypocritically</hi> tear the dead body of <hi>Hercules</hi> with a ſmiling counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. In a word, he is the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs</hi> of a <hi>Poet;</hi> whoſe ſepulchre is the <hi>Stocks,</hi> and his monument a <hi>Pillory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:49622:45"/>
               <head>The CHARACTER of a ſelf-conceited Fellow.</head>
               <p>HE is, I dare not ſay a Man, nor Boy; but in the Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis of both; yet he thinks only a beard is wanting to proclame his manhood; becauſe he has taken up Womens Smocks, he writes <hi>ſumptâ virili togâ,</hi> when indeed his wit is hardly out of the <hi>clouts.</hi> He is an <hi>Ape,</hi> that imitates both, but wanting the wit of the one, acts naturally the folly of the other. He thinks himſelf of deep judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet has nothing deep about him, but the pits of his noſe; which makes him boaſt of hills and dales in his own poſſeſſion. He affects two contraries; for he will be a laughing-ſtock to good
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49622:46"/>company, where his higheſt ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to be told he talks like an <hi>Apothecary;</hi> or elſe is the <hi>Bell-wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of children, fools, or <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> who have neither <hi>Engliſh</hi> enough to reprove his nonſenſe, nor to approve his <hi>no-wit;</hi> but paſs it over for jeſts by ignorant laughter. He is an <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> to miſ-lead fools by a ſhining no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is in him, or a blazing Star placed in the lower Regions of a <hi>Tavern;</hi> and a Cup in his brain, portends the birth of ſome prodigious conceit. To ingratiate himſelf into good company, he keeps conſtantly in pay a <hi>Regiment</hi> of jeſts and hard words, to ſalute their ears with a volley of non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe; which if they be not grac'd with laughter, he is nonſuited. But being diſ-robed of this ſtore, he whiſpers them of a Wench;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49622:46"/>and rather than want employment, will turn Pimp. You cannot pleaſe him unleſs you praiſe him; nor praiſe him, unleſs you flatter him. It is his <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> to move laughter; and if his <hi>jeſts</hi> will not do it, his <hi>geſture</hi> muſt; if neither, you may laugh at the Jeſtor. He moſt commonly procures friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with ſome <hi>wit,</hi> whom he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joins to be the foreman in the peal of laughter; who both to his face and behind his back, laughs at him. Much he affects to ſpeak ſome fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein Language, becauſe in all his Diſcourſe he would over-reach the <hi>capacity</hi> of an <hi>Engliſh-man.</hi> He whiſpers <hi>How d' you,</hi> as if 'twere Treaſon, in the ears of any new acquaintance, to make others think he is privy to their ſecrets. He always detracts from other mens worth behind their backs, as if he
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49622:47"/>knew by inſtinct others diſpraiſed him; and it goes hard if a man wears any clothes, but he will pick a hole in his coat. He hath not exchanged two words with Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in love (I had almoſt ſaid ſince he was of underſtanding) becauſe ſhe made him ſo low, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not over-look other mens actions; but to help this defect, he hath gotten the faculty of taking the wall of his betters; having nothing in himſelf worth his knowledge, he ſcorns <hi>noſcere ſeipſum.</hi> The <hi>thing</hi> is ſometimes Poetical wherein he caſts up his ignorance, to make it ſeem of high account; he writes like the <hi>Egyptian darkneſs,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſhews cunning; for when men laugh at his Verſes, he may ſay, they laugh at they know not what; and can boaſt of more than any Modern <hi>Poet,</hi> that he writes
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49622:47"/>above human apprehenſion. He carries ſuch a deep conceit of his own <hi>conceits,</hi> that he thinks no man worthy to underſtand them; nay he is ſuch a niggard, that he grudgeth himſelf the benefit. The Subject of his Fanſie is himſelf; wherein he truly ſhews himſelf <hi>poetical,</hi> if Fictions can do. He miſlikes every man after the firſt acquaintance; nay, grows weary of his native Countrey, and will travel; and his actions and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age therein, no tongue can expreſs but his own, for he may lie by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Himſelf is gone beyond the limits of my Paper, where my Pen nor can nor will follow him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:49622:48"/>
               <head>The Character of a <hi>City-Wit.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE is a gaudy <hi>Vacuum,</hi> gilded over with a few hard words, which he imagins to have a deep meaning, becauſe his dull ſenſe cannot dive into it; which with much pains he has weeded from Authors, and placed in Garriſon in a <hi>Common place-book,</hi> that he may draw out a Regiment of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruits when his wit is routed. His Diſcourſe is a Line of Sand, or a compoſition of ſo many <hi>foot</hi> and <hi>half-words,</hi> which being put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſpell <hi>non ſenſe.</hi> He admits not a word into his Society, under the degree of a <hi>Tetraſyllable;</hi> and takes all Diſcourſe by meaſure, not weight. He were the only man to be <hi>Minſhew</hi>'s Son, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49622:48"/>another <hi>Dictionary</hi> of hard words, had he but wit enough to ſpell them, or learning to tell their <hi>ſignification.</hi> Yet he thinks his noſe a <hi>Jacob</hi>'s <hi>Staff,</hi> able to calculate the height of any mans fanſie. By his tedious Diſcourſes of <hi>Heraldry,</hi> he would make you believe he were a Gentleman. And to gain Honour, he dares be a Soldier; and hath taken up Arms on his <hi>Signet,</hi> for defence of his little finger; but intends only to fight by the <hi>Heralds</hi> Book, where his valour will be ſeen by the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable hanging, drawing, and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of his innocent <hi>Coat.</hi> He had been preferred to a <hi>Trumpet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> place, but that he could ſound no Alarm, but his own praiſe. Had he but Poetry, he would out-vaper <hi>Ben;</hi> but he 'l not ſpeak a Verſe, leſt they ſhould be taken for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49622:49"/>of his own begetting, and known by their <hi>long legs.</hi> Beſides his ſpeeches are ſo maſterleſs, they think it againſt the Liberty of the Subject to be chained in a Verſe. In his Arguments his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions are more intricate than the Queſtion; and that man needs a deep reach that would define his definition. After many <hi>Pleonaſms</hi> and <hi>Circumlocutions,</hi> he is deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at length of a <hi>non ſequitur;</hi> yet makes no <hi>Concluſion,</hi> for his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is endleſs. You may be ſick of a <hi>Conſumption</hi> and cured, before he hath finiſhed a <hi>Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and 'tis a wonder if the <hi>Palſie</hi> in his tongue procure not the <hi>Frenſie</hi> in his head. <hi>Shews</hi> he prefers before <hi>ſubſtance;</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteems an <hi>Alcoran</hi> in folio before a pocket-<hi>Bible.</hi> He uſeth much to diſcommend himſelf; which we
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49622:49"/>muſt interpret as a praiſe, the clean contrary way; yet rather than loſe a drop of his praiſe, he will lick it up with his own tongue. The way to gain his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, is neither to underſtand him, nor be underſtood by him; he will then applaud the depth of your judgment; for it is his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty to think nothing <hi>deep,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be <hi>muddy.</hi> He accounts no man rich in wit, that does not <hi>gingle</hi> with it in every fools com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; he thinks not that a mans Ware-houſe may be full, whoſe Shop is empty; and a Fountain of Learning in that head, where there is no chanel in the tongue. He would fain be a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> for he is very <hi>peripatetical;</hi> and becauſe his wit is bald, he periwigs it with ſtoln <hi>combings,</hi> which he calls his own, becauſe he bought them, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49622:50"/>ſaith he ſtudied hard for them; but it was only to remember them; and if by chance any word do put out his head in company, and is not conceived, he'l ſwear 'tis an <hi>admirable conceit.</hi> Becauſe he is tall, he thinks his fanſie is predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant, and therefore is apt to inſult over any ſhort man, though he hath more underſtanding. He thinks every man barren of worth, that has not his tongue tipped with ſelf-praiſe; and thoſe unacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with wit, that have not their fanſies writ in their faces, perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous to every Reader. He is mighty glad if he be in company with a fool, and thinks him his foil, though indeed he be his look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſs. From the ruins of good Buildings he erects the <hi>Babels</hi> of his own conceit, and enriches his brain, which indeed is no other
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49622:50"/>but a Confuſion of Languages, where ſcarce one ſyllable under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands another. In the <hi>Church</hi> we muſt look for him in the higheſt Pew, but I am loth to ſtay his coming out, leſt he offend my ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach with ſome tedious Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe upon the Sermon; but there I leave him praying againſt a handſom Wife, leſt he be made a Cuckold; and againſt a witty Companion, leſt he be made a Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:49622:51"/>
               <head>The Character of a <hi>Humouriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HIs principal humour ſhall be my excuſe, that is, <hi>inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> 'tis hard to draw his Picture, that will not ſettle his countenance; therefore expect it rather in a <hi>Landskip</hi> than <hi>Statua.</hi> He is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled both in his actions and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; which ſhews his <hi>fanſie</hi> to predominate in him, rather than <hi>judgment;</hi> yet can it not be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that he is maſter of a ſound judgment, but he makes others, not himſelf the <hi>ſubject</hi> of it; being better able to inform others, than reform his life; and more able to <hi>declame</hi> againſt others vices, than <hi>reclame</hi> his own. His anger is more active than hot, rather ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching than burning; ſoon kindled,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49622:51"/>and as ſoon quencht. And though that man muſt needs make a ſtrange combuſtion in the State of his ſoul, that upon the landing of every <hi>Cock-boat</hi> ſets the <hi>Beacons</hi> on fire; yet becauſe his Reaſon ſtands Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinel, 'tis rather a diſorder than a mutiny. <hi>Virtue</hi> he more gazeth after than follows; or if he do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, it is rather with his tongue than feet; chuſing to talk with her ſooner than walk after her, and prefers a dram of <hi>Theorics</hi> before a pound of Practics. At the <hi>Game</hi> of unlawful Pleaſures he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be an <hi>Actor</hi> than a <hi>Spectator;</hi> ſeldom forſaking them till teeth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like he be forced to drop off through too much ſatiety. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy he will be in the midſt of <hi>mirth;</hi> certainly when he and his ſerious thoughts meet together (for they are ſtrangers) they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49622:52"/>company. <hi>Venus</hi> he eſteems above all the ſeven Planets; but had rather worſhip her in a <hi>Baudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe</hi> than in any of the twelve <hi>Celeſtial Signs.</hi> In his Materials he is a Gentleman; but Fortune hath caſt him in the <hi>City</hi> Mould. No doubt but age will reclame his unſtaidneſs; 'tis no great fault in a young Horſe to uſe unreaſonable mounting. To his friends he is rather formal than real, apt to truſt them with his perſon, not ſecrets. In a falling out of two friends, he will rather ſide with one, than bring both agreed; which is an <hi>Index</hi> of ſome indiſcretion; thereby he being ſure, of two friends to make one his enemy. He is no ſtranger to <hi>Poetry,</hi> which is Muſic in words, nor to Muſic, which is Poetry in ſound; yet ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther makes them his Sauce than
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49622:52"/>Meat. For <hi>Logic,</hi> which gives ſpeech ſubſtance; or <hi>Rhetoric,</hi> which gives it beauty; or <hi>Grammar,</hi> which gives a tongue to ſpeech itſelf; he has only ta'n a <hi>curſory</hi> view of the firſt of the three; but has rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated on the two laſt. But leſt I make my Garment too big for the Body which I took meaſure of; and being ſomething in haſte, I conclude with his own Proverb, <hi>By — I cannot ſtay.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J.B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>The Character of a <hi>Fudler.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE will only take a curſory view of him as he is in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> being not yet ſo unhappy to know him farther; but we may gheſs at the bulk of <hi>Hercules</hi> by his foot. He is a confuſed lump
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49622:53"/>moulded when Nature did all things in the dark; a <hi>Cub</hi> of the <hi>Chaos</hi> not lickt into form, rowled from <hi>Tavern</hi> to <hi>Tavern</hi> only to be drunk &amp; laught at; where he <hi>grunts</hi> out words as ill-ſhap'd and groſs as his perſon; and if his ſpeeches do chance to <hi>quarrel,</hi> you muſt take 'um as they fall out. His body is built like <hi>Babel,</hi> but never with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to reach Heaven; the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were confounded, and put Mortar where Gold ſhould be. His ordinary Diſcourſe is only ſcurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and profaneneſs in a miſcella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, boiled together in huge quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of <hi>Sack,</hi> which he carves to his friends as prime Dainties. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than his <hi>Jeſts</hi> ſhall want fire, he will light them at Gods Altar; and though a Conceit grow on the Banks of <hi>Hell,</hi> he will adventure to fetch it; not caring to gain his
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49622:53"/>conceit, though he loſe his ſoul. In company he monopolizeth all the Diſcourſe to himſelf; not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding if his <hi>tongue</hi> keep on a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop before, how far his <hi>underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> loiters behind. Sometimes his Wit ſtumbles on a Jeſt, as he that ſhoots thick, ſometimes may his; and then you will do him a great diſcourteſie, if you do not laugh; but the main body of his diſcourſe is a <hi>Wild-gooſe chaſe</hi> after ſome prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Wit, which he cannot catch. When he ſpeaks, 'tis not the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his tongue, but the ratling of his brains; and 'tis worth our wonder, that his belly ſhould be ſo full, and head ſo empty; but the fulneſs of the one is the empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the other. His belly, like the great Fiſh, eats up all the reſt of his limbs, yet his wit is as <hi>fat</hi> as that. He has ſpent much time
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49622:54"/>in travel to learn to be an <hi>Aſs,</hi> all that he has ſeen is the <hi>Tun</hi> at <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleburgh,</hi> which he ſtudies to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate; and all that he hath brought away, is the exact managing of his <hi>Fork</hi> at Table. He walks in the ſtreets like a Rundlet of Sack on two poſts; and where'ere he goes, he carries a fool with him. His ſtudy is old Jeſts and Tales; his recreation, Drinking; and his main occupation is Wenching. But I fear I have been too long in his company; by this time he is drunk, 'tis time to leave him leſt he ſpue in our faces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:49622:54"/>
               <head>A Solicitor</head>
               <p>IS one of the blades of <hi>Corn</hi> that ſprings from the <hi>Ilian</hi> ruines, whoſe <hi>ears</hi> grow up for the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of a <hi>Pillory.</hi> His Profeſſion is originally like a <hi>Cuckow,</hi> from the <hi>Neſt</hi> of another <hi>Trade;</hi> where he has learned wrangling and knave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry enough in his own <hi>Cauſes</hi> to ſpoil another mans. With the ſweetned <hi>Ingredients</hi> of <hi>City-fraud</hi> he compounds himſelf (though ſimple enough) for any villany. He is truly ſaid to <hi>follow a Cauſe;</hi> but a ſmall Bribe will <hi>lame</hi> him ſo, that he will never come near it. He is one of <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes, that fires all about him; but that his fire is generally in his <hi>noſe,</hi> as well as his <hi>tail.</hi> His ambition is ſo
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49622:55"/>low, not to have his Chamber in an Inns-of-Court, but in an Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of the City; a Tavern is his <hi>form,</hi> and licking of Pots his <hi>Law.</hi> Moſt of his Actions are <hi>Aſſaults</hi> or <hi>Slanders;</hi> which are broacht where his Ale is, in a <hi>Cellar;</hi> and after a long circumſtance, <hi>center</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves where they begun; where his fooliſh Client, being weary of his fruitleſs endleſs Suit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting the idle expence of his Money for an imaginary <hi>vacuum,</hi> called <hi>getting the day;</hi> like the <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,</hi> that blows away his <hi>Silver</hi> and <hi>Lungs,</hi> for that <hi>Fools</hi> (rather than <hi>Philoſophers</hi>) Stone; do's by his wholſom advice, when his Money is ſpent, refer his Suit to <hi>Arbitrators</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpires;</hi> whoſe Verdict is after a long debate, A Supper for themſelves at the equal charge of both Parties; That both
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49622:55"/>muſt be ſorry for what they have done (as they have good cauſe) and ſit down by their loſſes. He ſeldom gets any conſiderable preferment, but among <hi>Fiſh-wives</hi> or <hi>Watermen,</hi> or in a <hi>Countrey Village,</hi> where all ſtand in awe of him, and ſlander him with the Title of <hi>Maſter Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer. Ignorance</hi> and <hi>beggery</hi> makes him reſolute that he dares thruſt his head into any employment. At laſt, having run through the <hi>Zodiac</hi> of all Courts, if he ſcape the preferment of the Gallows, he caſts Anchor in a Gaol, or a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel; and there we leave him.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
